Guide to the McKim Mead and White Architectural Records circa 1875-1950 PR 42
New-York Historical Society
- Series IV: Photographs, circa 1880s-1960s
  - Subseries IV.C: Large Photographs, undated
    - Villard Houses, Whitelaw Reid, interior detail of a mosaic (Box 66)
    - New York Life, exterior (Box 66)
    - National City Bank, interior (Box 66)
    - New York Post Office, interior (Box 66)
    - Tiffany Residence, exterior (Box 66)
    - Gorham Building, exterior (Box 66)
    - Yosemite Building, detail of doorway? (Box 66)
    - Century Club, 2 views of the interior (Box 66)
    - Washington Arch, 2 construction scenes (Box 66)
    - Frederick W. Vanderbilt House, Hyde Park, NY, 2 views (Box 67)
    - Osborn Residence, 2 views (Box 67)
    - Shepard Residence, 5 views (Box 67)
    - Low, Carroll B., Residence (Box 67)
    - Johnson, Harold F., Residence (Box 67)
    - E.D. Morgan, Residence, RI (Box 67)
    - Tuxedo Park Studio (Box 67)
    - Unidentified city residence (Box 67)
    - State House, RI (Box 67)
    - William McKinley Monument (Box 67)
    - Pennsylvania Railroad Station, waiting room, Newark, NJ (Box 67)
    - Col. Shaw Monument, Boston, MA (Box 67)
    - Free Christian Church, Andover (Box 67)
    - New York Life Building, Omaha, NE (Box 67)
    - Tennessee Victory Statue (Box 67)
    - National Bank, Shreveport, LA, 2 views (Box 67)
    - Franklin National Bank (Box 67)
    - Boston Public Library, reading room (Box 67)
    - Unidentified interior (Box 67)
    - Brooklyn Botanical Garden Building, Brooklyn, NY (Box 67)
    - Unidentified bridge (Box 67)
    - Columbia University, NYC, 4 views (Box 67)
    - General plan for Amherst College, Amherst, MA (Box 68)
    - Amherst Alumni House, Amherst, MA, bound oversize booklet with floor plans and cross-sections (Box 68)
    - Waterman Memorial, University of Vermont photograph (Box 68)
    - USA Infantry School, Fort Benning, GA, photograph (Box 68)
    - E.D. Morgan, Newport, RI, drawing (Box 68)
    - Unidentified college buildings (Box 68)
    - Harvard University Graduate School of Business Administration, Boston, MA, plan (Box 68)
    - Section, theatre for Amherst College, Amherst, MA (Box 68)
    - Amherst College, Amherst, MA, mounted photograph (very poor condition; broken in two pieces) (Box 68)
  - Subseries IV.D: Glass Negatives
    This subseries includes approximately 600 8 x 10 inch glass negatives. There is no inventory of these.
- Series V: Scrapbooks and photograph albums
  This series includes 30 blank-paged leather-bound volumes with photographs, maps, sketches, and/or floor plans pasted in. Some of the albums have been disbound and re-housed in folders due to their deteriorating condition. Most albums depict MMW projects and are devoted to either a particular project or a general category of work. There are also a few albums of non-MMW work which probably served as sourcebooks for the firm's architects to draw ideas from.
  Detailed inventories for some of the scrapbooks are available on-site.
  - Photograph scrapbook, New York University, 1898 (Volume SB-1)
    Scrapbook contains maps, sketches, and photographs of building exteriors, fields, barns, dormitories, the library, Havemeyer Chemical Laboratory, staircases, general construction, and the Hall of Languages in University Heights. 1898.
  - Clippings scrapbook (mainly non-MM&W Beaux-Arts competitions), undated (Volume SB-2)
    This album does not appear to contain the work of MM&W. Instead, the majority of photographs and sketches concern themselves with various Beaux-Arts Architects and competitions. There are several decorative elements at the beginning of the book.
  - Scrapbook of MM&W Commissions, 1870-1888 (Volume SB-3.1)
    Existence and Location of Copies
    The original is restricted due to condition issues. A photocopied version (Volume SB-3.2) is available for researchers.
    Comprehensive collection of plans, photographs, designs and articles relating to McKim, Mead and White commissions. There are several unidentified buildings. Articles pertain to the building, construction, and controversy (such as the trustees of the Boston Public Library choosing McKim, Mead and White over the Boston city architect).
  - Scrapbook of MM&W Commissions, 1870-1888 (facsimile) (Volume SB-3.2)
  - Record Work, 1888-1906 (Volume SB-4.1)
    Disbound scrapbook of MM&W works-in-progress.
    Folder 1 includes images of ceiling details, doors under construction, columns waiting to be installed, and crude sculptures. The only dated photograph is from 1894, for the Power House in Niagara Falls, NY. Majority of pictures are unlabeled.
    Folder 2 includes interiors, tombstones, cemeteries, unidentified houses, Shinnecock Hills, the Ascension Church, and sculptures of lions and children.
    Folder 3 includes an urn, the construction of Staatsburgh, Ophir Farm, the rotunda at the University of Virginia, 110 Bleecker Street, Joseph's Pulitzer's door, a storehouse, sculptures, and unidentified buildings. Several photographs include workmen and pedestrians.
    Folder 4 includes the Chandler, Whitney, and Williams houses under construction, along with the unveiling of the Peter Cooper Memorial. Scenes from what appear to be the World's Fair, and decorative elements belonging to unidentified residences also appear in the folder.
    Folder 5 includes the George Williams house, the Vanderbilt residence, the Duseen (?) building, and a mausoleum. Several sites and buildings are unidentifiable.
    Folder 6 includes Ferncliff Casino, the Hecker Mausoleum site, the Twombley plot, the Philadelphia Art Museum, Whitelaw Reid residence, and the Paulist Fathers Church.
    Folder 7 includes Beacon Rock, the Pierpont Morgan Library, Harvard Gates, and the Knickerbocker Trust Company. There are multiple street scenes that include the Hotel Manhattan, Grand Central Station, the Astor, and the Old Waldorf-Astoria Hotel.
    Folder 8 includes the Ochre Point home of Robert Goelet, and at least two non-MM&W projects: the improvement of Copley Square, and a Roman School. There are also several unidentified houses and churches.
    Folder 9 includes projects that were not designed by MM&W, including the Roman School, Mr. Treat Campbell at 298 Broadway, Fort Greene Park, Holt Monument, and what appears to be a triumphal arch. There are also several photographs highlighting construction workers, cows, landscapes, and a man standing between a column and a lightpost.
  - Record Work, 1833-1909 (Volume SB-4.2)
    The majority of designs are by the firm of McKim, Mead and White. Other architects are J.H. Duncan, Seth Greer, and U.H. Mullins. There are photographs of proposed sites, additions, interiors, and even an analysis of capitals. Grant's Tomb, by J.H. Duncan, is also included.
  - Scrapbook of architectural details (Volume SB-5.1)
    Original drawings of architectural details such as columns and arches
  - Scrapbook of architectural details (Volume SB-5.2)
  - Photo Album A-Z (folders 1-6), 1901-1914 (Volume SB-6.1)
    Folder 1 includes what appear to be mausoleums, and decorative elements for the exterior.
    Folder 2 includes exterior photographs of residences and buildings, several photographs show the stages of construction. Some pictures are closeups of entryways. Also shows crowds of men outside the New York Herald, and the statue being placedon top of the building.
    Folder 3 includes buildings in various states of construction and finish, and exterior renovations. There are also street scenes, and several pastoral scenes in photographs. One interesting photograph in folder 3 features only a man in a field of cows. Folder 4 includes exteriors and interiors of buildings, along with street scenes. Photographs show construction, workers, pedestrians, and several photographs are of architectural models for the Girard Trust Company. Clubs, a high school, and the Metropolitan Museum of Art also feature.
  - Photo Album A-Z (folders 7-11), undated (Volume SB-6.2)
    Folder 9 includes photographs the floor test in the Amherst Laboratory, and the coffered ceiling detail of Winnipeg Bank.
  - Early work of firm (Volume SB-7)
  - New York State College of Agriculture (Cornelius White, architect) (Volume SB-7)
  - Schools and Colleges (Volume SB-8)
  - Sculptures and Monuments, 1889-1912 (Volume SB-9)
    Majority of work in album not done by McKim, Mead and White. This appears to be a scrapbook of ideas, inspiration, and competition in the fields of architecture and sculpture.
    One object of note in Folder 2 is a painting of Lady Charles Spencer. Folders 3 and 4 focus on expositions and exhibitions at the end of the 19th and beginning of the 20th century, including the Pan-American Exposition, Buffalo, NY; Louisiana Purchase Exposition, St. Louis, MO; Trans-Mississippi Exhibition, Omaha, NE; World's Columbia Exposition, Chicago, IL; and the Exposition of 1900, Paris, France. Architects are noted whenever possible.
  - Parks, monuments and landscape gardening (Volume SB-10)
  - Modern sculpture (Volume SB-11)
    Consists of photographs of non-MM&W sculpture. Most pages are blank.
  - Office Work (Volume SB-12)
    Mostly exterior photographs of residences, the RI state capital building, a statue, and New York office buildings.
  - Country work, 1879-1912 (Volume SB-13.1)
    Disbound photo album of commissioned McKim, Mead and White residences, buildings, gazebos and clubs. Interior photographs are included. Highlights include Box Hill, Stanford White's residence in St. James (Folder 1); the Orange Y.M.C.A. building (Folder 2); and a spectacular bird's eye view of Naugatuck, CT (Folder 7). Also features work commissioned by Edwin Dennison Morgan, John Jacob Astor IV, C.H. Mackay, George G. King, University of Virginia, L.C. Hanna, the Sherry Casino, and Dr. R.H. Derby.
  - Country work (Volume SB-13.2)
    Bound album of commissioned McKim, Mead and White residence, buildings, gazebos and clubs.
  - Foreign work (folders 1-6), 1902-1910 (Volume SB-14.1)
    None of the work represented in the album was designed by McKim, Mead and White. This most probably served as an architectural sourcebook for the architects to draw ideas from. Photographs show architectural details, interiors, facades, tombs, monuments, and other sculptural and architectural elements. Also includes copies of floor plans for many palaces and residences.
  - Foreign work (folders 7-14), 1902-1910 (Volume SB-14.2)
  - Iron work, 1897-1902 (Volume SB-15)
    Architectural scrapbook of ideas for the firm of McKim, Mead and White. Iron-work dominates the folder. Many photographs are from the Museo Nazionale in Naples, Italy. There is one double-helix staircase that bears a strong resemblance to the double-helix staircase at Rosecliff, a mansion the firm designed and built between 1897-1902.
  - Houses - Twombley, Nickerson and others (Volume SB-16)
    Includes work commissioned by Hamilton McKay Twombly, owner of Florham Farms in Madison, NJ, and a residence for George A. Nickerson, in Boston, MA. Also included is another unidentified residence.
  - Walker O. Cain & Associates, Book of photographs by Mr. Mead, 1883-1907 (Volume SB-17)
    Subject matter includes buildings, plans, decorative elements, and elevations from apartment houses to the Payne Whitney House (includes many unidentified projects). There are also photographs of construction sites, alleyways, streets, and parks.
  - Girard Trust (Volume SB-18)
  - Bellevue Hospital (Volume SB-19)
  - Bank of Montreal (Volume SB-20.1)
  - Bank of Montreal (Volume SB-20.2)
  - Report of the Washington Park Commission (Volume SB-21)
  - Henry B. Hollins Townhouse (Volume SB-22)
  - Stanford White residence - St. James (Volume SB-23)
  - Stanford White residence - 121 East 21st Street (Volume SB-24.1)
  - Stanford White residence - 121 East 21st Street (Volume SB-24.2)
  - Stanford White residence - 121 East 21st Street (Volume SB-24.3)
  - Clarence MacKay residence (Harbor Hill) (Volume SB-25)
  - Hoving residence (?) (Volume SB-26)
  - H.W. Poor residence (Volume SB-27)
  - Boston Public Library (Volume SB-28)
  - University of Virginia, 1895-1898 (Volume SB-29)
    Photographs of the construction and completion of the Rotunda, buildings in the South Lawn Complex, and Rouss Hall are featured in the album. Also included are interior photographs, and several shots of arcades.
  - Columbia University (folders 1-6), 1895-1897 (Volume SB-30.1)
    Several photographs show construction workers.
    Photographs in the first 5 folders focus on the construction of the Columbia College Library. A few photographs from the completed building show students using the Reading Room. Folders 5 and 6 show construction on the University Building.
  - Columbia University (folders 7-12) (Volume SB-30.2)
    Folder 7 shows the construction of and completed Physics Building. Folders 8 and 9 focus on the Natural Science Building. There are other photographs in folder 9 of the Engineering Building. The Chemistry Building is shown in folders 9 and 10. Folder 12 has a few photos of Hamilton Hall.
- Series VI: Newspaper and journal clippings
  This series consists primarily of newspaper and magazine clippings concerning McKim, Mead and White projects; also included are special reprints of clippings and of published photographs. The clippings were originally pasted in volumes which have been disbound due to their deteriorating condition.
  - Clippings 1889-1901 (Box C-1)
    This material has been microfilmed and will be brought to the researcher in that format.
  - Clippings 1892-1901 (Box C-2)
  - Clippings 1906-1911 (Box C-3)
  - Clippings 1910-1917 (Box C-4.1)
  - Clippings 1910-1917 (Box C-4.2)
  - Clippings 1919-1929 (Box C-5)
  - Journal clippings 1913-1918 (Box C-6)
    Includes journal clippings, pictures from journals, drawings and plans. Subjects includes statutes, monuments, residences, banks, memorials, clubs, university buildings, and a laboratory for the Brooklyn Botanic Gardens.
  - Boston Public Library (Box C-7)
  - Clippings scrapbook of MM&W buildings (Box C-8)
  - Journal articles on architecture (Box C-9)
  - New York City Architect, Vol. 2, No. 5, "City Investing Building: A Tribute.", 1908 May (Box C-10)
- Series VII: Financial Records books
  This series includes 54 volumes of financial records books, divided into the following seven categories: bill books, cash books, journal books, ledger books, contract books, and miscellaneous financial records books. The bill books include typed carbon copies of accounts; the remaining books consist primarily of handwritten financial account ledgers.
  For additional copies of bills and statements, see Series II, Correspondence.
  - Subseries V.1: Bill Books
    - Bill book July 1878 - March 1884 (Volume FR-1)
    - Bill book April 1884-May 1887 (Volume FR-2)
    - Bill book May 1887-November 1890 (Volume FR-3)
    - Bill book November 1890-October 1893 (Volume FR-4)
    - Bill book October 1893-July 1896 (Volume FR-5)
    - Bill book August 1896-June 1899 (Volume FR-6)
    - Bill book July 1899-November 1902 (Volume FR-7)
    - Bill book December 1902-March 1906 (Volume FR-8)
    - Bill book March 1906-December 1909 (Volume FR-9)
    - Bill book January 1910-March 1913 (Volume FR-10)
    - Bill book March 1913-December 1916 (Volume FR-11)
    - Bill book January 1917-December 1921 (Volume FR-12)
    - Bill book December 1921-April 1925 (Volume FR-13)
    - Bill book May 1925-October 1927 (Volume FR-14)
    - Bill book October 1927-January 1931 (Volume FR-15)
    - Bill book January 1931-April 1938 (Volume FR-16)
    - Bill book May 1938-December 1947 (Volume FR-17)
    - Bill book September 1933-December 1948 (Volume FR-18)
    - Bill book Summary 1890-1940 (Volume FR-19)
  - Subseries V.2: Cash Books
    - Cash book April 1894-June 1899 (Volume FR-20)
    - Cash book June 1899-December 1903 (Volume FR-21)
    - Cash book January 1904-August 1909 (Volume FR-22)
    - Cash book September 1909-December 1916 (Volume FR-23)
    - Cash book January 1917-June 1922 (Volume FR-24)
    - Cash book July 1922-August 1926 (Volume FR-25)
    - Cash book September 1926-December 1930 (Volume FR-26)
    - Cash book January 1931-September 1937 (Volume FR-27)
    - Cash book October 1937-December 1944 (Volume FR-28)
  - Subseries V.3: Journal Books
    - Journal January 1882-May 1888 (Volume FR-29)
    - Journal June 1888-February 1894 (Volume FR-30)
    - Journal March 1894-January 1901 (Volume FR-31)
    - Journal February 1901-December 1906 (Volume FR-32)
    - Journal January 1907-August 1915 (Volume FR-33)
    - Journal September 1915-August 1921 (Volume FR-34)
    - Journal September 1921-December 1926 (Volume FR-35)
    - Journal January 1927-June 1933 (Volume FR-36)
    - Journal July 1933-December 1942 (Volume FR-37)
  - Subseries V.4: Ledger Books
    - Ledger 1882-1890 (Volume FR-38)
    - Ledger 1890-1899 (Volume FR-39)
    - Ledger 1899-1906 (Volume FR-40)
    - Ledger 1906-1917 (Volume FR-41)
    - Ledger 1917-19126 (Volume FR-42)
    - Ledger 1927-1940 (Volume FR-43)
  - Subseries V.5: Contract Books
    - Contracts 1903-1907 (Volume FR-44)
    - Contracts 1905-1910 (Volume FR-45)
    - Contracts 1914-1922 (Volume FR-46)
    - Contracts 1921-1923 (Volume FR-47)
    - Contracts 1923-1925 (Volume FR-48)
    - Contracts 1926-1930 (Volume FR-49)
    - Contracts 1931-1942 (Volume FR-50)
  - Subseries V.6: Other Financial Records Books
    - Billing Correspondence 1903-1904 (Volume FR-51)
    - Loan Record 1904-1920 (Volume FR-52)
    - Petty Cash Book 1904-1920 (Volume FR-53)
    - Hotel Pennsylvania data book (Volume FR-54)
- Series VIII: Publications
  This subseries includes two boxes of what appear to be proof plates for A Monograph of the Works of McKim, Mead and White, 1879-1915, published in phases from 1915 to 1920, as well as the plates for McKim, Mead and White houses and casinos featured in George William Sheldon's Artistic Country-Seats, published in 1886.
  Also included is the firm's copy of the 1899 Sanborn fire insurance Atlas of New York City.
  The Print Room also holds a complete set of the original plates for A Monograph of the Works of McKim, Mead and White, 1879-1915. The call number for the set is Print Room Rare NA737.MR A5 1915.
  - Plate proofs, A Monograph of the Works of McKim, Mead and White, 1879-1915, Volume 1. (Box P-1)
  - Plate proofs, A Monograph of the Works of McKim, Mead and White, 1879-1915, Volume 2. (Box P-2)
  - Plates for MMW houses and casinos featured in George William Sheldon's Artistic Country-Seats, 1886. (Box P-3)
  - Sanborn Atlas of New York City, Volume 1: Battery-14th Street, 1899 (Box P-4)
  - Sanborn Atlas of New York City, Volume 2: 14th-59th Street, 1899 (Box P-5)
  - Sanborn Atlas of New York City, Volume 3: 59th-110th Street, 1899 (Box P-6)
  - Sanborn Atlas of New York City, Volume 4: 110th-145th Street, 1899 (Box P-7)
  - Sanborn Atlas of New York City, Volume 5: 145th Street-Spuyten Duyvil, 1905 (Box P-7)